<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="concepts" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Basic VSIPL Concepts</title>

  <section>
    <title>General Library Design Principles</title>

    <para>The purpose of the Vector, Signal, and Image Processing Library
    (VSIPL) standard is to support portable, high performance application
    programs. The standard is based upon existing libraries that have evolved
    and matured over decades of scientific and engineering computing. A layer
    of abstraction is added to support portability across diverse memory and
    processor architectures. The primary design focus of the standard has been
    embedded signal processing platforms. Enhanced portability of workstation
    applications is a side benefit.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Elements are stored in one dimensional data arrays, which appear
        to the application programmer as a single contiguous block of
        memory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Data arrays can be viewed as either real or complex vectors,
        matrices, or tensors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All operations on data arrays are performed indirectly through
        view objects, each of which specify a particular view of a data array
        with a particular offset, length(s) and stride(s).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In general, the application programmer cannot combine operators
        in a single statement to evaluate expressions. Operators which return
        scalar may be combined, but most operators will return a view type or
        are void and may not be combined.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Operators are restricted to views of a data array that can be
    specified by an offset, lengths and strides. Views that are more arbitrary
    are converted into these simple views by functions like gather and back
    again by functions like scatter. VSIPL does not support triangular or
    sparse matrices very well, though future extensions might address
    these.</para>

    <para>The main difference between the proposed VSIPL standard and existing
    libraries is a cleaner encapsulation of the above principles through an
    “object-based” design. All of the view attributes are encapsulated in
    opaque objects <footnote>
        <para>Object opacity is achieved through the technique of “incomplete
        typedef,” described in the section on implementation.</para>
      </footnote>. The object can only be created, accessed and destroyed via
    library functions, which reference it via a pointer.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Memory Management</title>

    <para>The management of memory is important to efficient algorithm
    development. This is especially true in embedded systems, many of which
    are memory limited. In VSIPL, memory management is handled by the
    implementation. This section describes VSIPL memory management and how the
    user interacts with VSIPL objects.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Terminology</title>

      <para>The terms user data, VSIPL data, admitted, and released are used
      throughout this document when describing memory allocation. It is
      important that the reader understand the terms that are defined in this
      section below, and in the Glossary above.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Object Memory Allocation</title>

      <para>All objects in VSIPL consist of abstract data types (ADT) which
      contain attributes defining the underlying data accessed by the object.
      Certain of the attributes are accessible to the application programmer
      via access functions; however, there may be any number of attributes
      assigned by the VSIPL library developer for its internal use. Each time
      an object is defined, memory must be allocated for the ADT. All VSIPL
      objects are allocated by VSIPL library functions. There is no method by
      which the application programmer may allocate space for these objects
      outside of VSIPL.</para>

      <para>Most VSIPL objects are relatively small and of fixed size;
      however, some of the objects created for signal processing or linear
      algebra may allocate large workspaces.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Data Memory Allocation</title>

      <para>A data array is an area of memory where data is stored. Data
      arrays in VSIPL exist in one of two logical data spaces. These are the
      user data space, and VSIPL data space. VSIPL functions may only operate
      on data in VSIPL space. User supplied functions may only operate on data
      in user space. Data may be moved between these logical spaces. Depending
      on the specific implementation, this move may incur actual data movement
      penalties or may simply be a bookkeeping procedure. The user should
      consider the data in VSIPL space to be inaccessible except through VSIPL
      functions.</para>

      <para>A data array allocated by the application, using any method not
      part of the VSIPL standard, is considered to be a user data array. The
      application has a pointer to the user data array and knowledge of its
      type and size. Therefore the application can access a user data array
      directly using pointers, although it is not always correct to do
      so.</para>

      <para>A data array allocated by a VSIPL function call is referred to as
      a VSIPL data array. The user has no proper method to retrieve a pointer
      to such a data array; it may only be accessed via VSIPL function
      calls.</para>

      <para>Users may access data arrays in VSIPL space using an entity
      referred to as a block. The data array associated with a block is a
      contiguous series of elements of a given type. There is one block type
      for each type of data processed by VSIPL.</para>

      <para>There are two categories of blocks, user blocks and VSIPL blocks.
      A user block is one that has been associated with a user data array. A
      VSIPL block is one that has been associated with a VSIPL data array. The
      data array referenced by the block is referred to as being “bound” to
      the block. The user must provide a pointer to the associated data for a
      user block. The VSIPL library will allocate space for the data
      associated with a VSIPL block. Blocks can also be created without any
      data and then associated with data in user space. The process of
      associating user space data with a block is called “binding.” A block
      which does not have data bound to it may not be used, as there is no
      data to operate on.</para>

      <para>A block that has been associated with data may exist in one of two
      states, admitted and released. The data in an admitted block is in the
      logical VSIPL data space, and the data in a released block is in the
      logical user data space. The process of moving data from the logical
      user data space to the logical VSIPL data space is called admission; the
      reverse process is called release.</para>

      <para>Data in an admitted block is owned by the VSIPL library, and VSIPL
      functions operate on this data under the assumption that the data will
      only be modified using VSIPL functions. VSIPL blocks are always in the
      admitted state. User blocks may be in an admitted state. User data in an
      admitted block shall not be operated on except by VSIPL functions.
      Direct manipulation of user data bound to an admitted block via pointers
      to the allocated memory is incorrect and may cause erroneous
      behavior.</para>

      <para>Data in a released block may be accessed by the user, but VSIPL
      functions should not perform computation on it. User blocks are created
      in the released state. The block must be admitted to VSIPL before VSIPL
      functions can operate on the data bound to the block. A user block may
      be admitted for use by VSIPL and released when direct access to the data
      is needed by the application program. A VSIPL block may not be
      released.</para>

      <para>Blocks represent logically contiguous data areas in memory
      (physical layout is undefined for VSIPL space), but users often wish to
      operate on non-contiguous sub-sets of these data areas. To provide
      support for such operations, VSIPL requires that users operate on the
      data in a block through another object type called a view. Views allow
      the user to specify noncontiguous subsets of a data array and inform
      VSIPL how the data will be accessed (for example, as a vector or
      matrix). When creating a vector view, the user specifies an offset into
      the block, a view length, and a stride value which specifies the number
      of elements (defined in the type of the block) to advance between each
      access. Thus, for a block whose corresponding data array contains four
      elements, a view with an offset value of zero, a stride of two, and a
      length of two represents a logical data set consisting of members zero
      and two of the original block. For a matrix view, stride and length
      parameters are specified in each dimension, and a single offset is
      specified. By varying the stride, row-major or column-major matrices can
      be created.</para>

      <para>A block may have any number of views created on it: this allows
      the user to use vector views to access particular rows or columns of a
      matrix view, for example. Since the blocks are typed, views are also
      typed; however, because views also include usage information (e.g.
      vector or matrix), there are multiple view types for each block type
      corresponding to how the data will be accessed. These types are
      immutable; thus for example, a block cannot have both integer and float
      views associated with it. This would not be useful in any event because
      the data layout inside VSIPL space is vendor specific.</para>

      <para>New views of a block may be created directly using a block object,
      or indirectly using a previously created view of the block. Except for
      finding the real or imaginary view of a complex view all views may be
      created directly using the block object.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Structure of a VSIPL application</title>

    <para>Although there are a number of ways to program an application, the
    basic VSIPL program consists of the following sequence:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/structure.svg" format="SVG" scale="60"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/structure.png" format="PNG" scale="60"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>A VSIPL program must initialize the VSIPL library with a call to
    vsip_init before calling any other VSIPL function. Any program that uses
    VSIPL and that terminates must call vsip_finalize before terminating. See
    the Support chapter for additional conditions and restrictions on these
    functions.</para>
  </section>
</section>
