<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix version="5.0" xml:id="glossary"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Glossary</title>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Admitted</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Block state where the data array (memory) and associated views
        are available for VSIPL computations, and not available for user I/O
        or access.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Attribute</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Characteristic or state of an object, such as admitted/released,
        stride, or length.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Binary Function</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A function with two input arguments.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A data storage abstraction representing contiguous data elements
        consisting of a data array and a VSIPL block object.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Block Object</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Descriptor for a data array and its attributes, including a
        reference to the data array, the state of the block, data type and
        size.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Block Offset</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The number of elements from the start of a block. A view with a
        block offset of zero starts at the beginning of the block.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Boolean</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Used to represent the values of true and false, where false is
        always zero, and true is non-zero.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Bound</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A view or block is bound to a data array if it references the
        data array.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Cloned View</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An exact duplicate of a view object.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Column</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Rightmost dimension in a matrix.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Column Stride</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The number of block elements between successive elements within
        a column.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Complex Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Block containing only complex elements. There are two formats
        for released complex blocks – split and interleaved. The complex data
        format for admitted complex blocks are not specified by this
        standard.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Conformant Views</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Views that are the correct shape/size for a given
        computation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>const Object</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An object that is not modified by the function, although data
        referenced by the const object may be modified.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Create</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>To allocate memory for an object and initialize it (if
        appropriate).</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Data Array</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Memory where data is stored.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Derived Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A real block derived from a complex block. Note that the only
        way to create a derived block is to create a derived view of the real
        or complex component of a split complex view. In all other cases,
        retrieving the block from a view returns a reference to the original
        block.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Derived View</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A derived view is a view created using a VSIPL function whose
        arguments include another view (a parent view). The derived view's
        data is some subset of the parent view's data. The data subset depends
        on the function call, and is physically co-located in memory with the
        parent view's data.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Destroy</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>To release the memory allocated to an object.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Development Library</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An implementation of VSIPL that maximizes error reporting at the
        possible expense of performance.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Domain</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The set of all valid input values to a function.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Element</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The atomic portion of data associated with a block or a view.
        For example, an element of a complex block of precision double is a
        complex number of precision double; for a view of type float an
        element is a single float number.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Hermitian Transpose</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Conjugate transpose.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Hint</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Information provided by the user to some VSIPL functions to aid
        optimization. Hints are optional and may be ignored by the
        implementation. Wrong hints may result in incorrect behavior.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Implementor</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The individual or group creating a VSIPL implementation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>In-Place</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A type of algorithm implementation in which the memory used to
        hold the input to an algorithm is overwritten (completely or
        partially) with the output data.  Often referred to in the context of
        an FFT algorithm.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Interleaved Complex</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage format for user data arrays where the real and complex
        element components alternate in physical memory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Kernel</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The filter vector used in a FIR filter, or the vector or matrix
        used as the weights in a convolution.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Length</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Number of elements in a view along a view dimension.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>M-ary Function</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A function with M arguments.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Matrix</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A two dimensional view.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>N-ary Function</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A null-ary function without input arguments (for by-element
        functions, function of element index, not element value).</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Opaque</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An opaque object may not be manipulated by simple assignment
        statements. Its attributes must be set/retrieved through access
        functions. All VSIPL objects are opaque.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Out-of-place</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>If none of the output views in a function call overlap the input
        views, the function is considered out-of-place.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Overlapped</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Indicates that two or more views or blocks share one or more
        memory locations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Portable Precision</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A data type with a guarantee of a specified minimum precision or
        an exact precision on all supported implementations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Production Library</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A VSIPL implementation that maximizes performance at the
        possible expense of not detecting user errors.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Range</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Valid output values from a function.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Real Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A block containing only real elements.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Region of Support</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>For neighborhood operations (i.e. FIR filtering, convolution,
        …), the non-zero values in the kernel, or the output. [ 3x3 FIR filter
        has a “kernel region of support” of 3x3.]</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Released</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Block state where the associated data array is available for
        user I/O and application access, but not available for VSIPL
        computations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Varlistentry</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Left-most dimension of a matrix.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Varlistentry Stride</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The number of block elements between successive elements within
        a varlistentry.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Split Complex</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage format for released complex blocks where the real
        element components are stored in one physically contiguous data array,
        and the imaginary components are stored in a separate physically
        contiguous data array.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Stride</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Distance between successive elements of the block data array in
        a view along a view dimension. Strides can be positive, negative, or
        zero.  </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Subview</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A derived view that describes a subset of the data from the
        original view, and is the same type as the original view.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Tensor</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>An n-dimensional matrix. VSIPL only supports 3 dimensional
        tensors (3-tensor). The three dimensions are referred to as X, Y and
        Z.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Ternary Function</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A function with 3 input arguments.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Unary Function</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A function with a single input argument.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>User Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A block which is associated with user data arrays. User blocks
        are created in the released state and may be admitted and
        released.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>User Data Array</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Memory that has been allocated by the application for the
        storage of data using some functionality not part of the VSIPL
        standard.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Vector</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A one dimensional view.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>View</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A portion of a block, and a view object describing it. The view
        object has structural information allowing the data to be interpreted
        as a one, two or three-dimensional array for arithmetic
        processing.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>View Dimension</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A view represents a one, two, or three dimensional data
        organization termed respectively a vector, matrix or tensor. A view
        dimension represents one of the standard directions of these data
        representations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>View Object</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>A description of a portion of a block including structural
        information that allows the data to be interpreted as a one, two or
        three-dimensional array for arithmetic processing. Attributes of the
        view object include offset, stride(s) and length(s).</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>VSIPL Block</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Block referencing or bound to VSIPL data. A VSIPL block is
        created in the admitted state and may not be released.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>VSIPL Data Array</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Memory that has been allocated for the storage of data using
        some functionality that is part of the VSIPL standard.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</appendix>
