<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="intro" 
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>Scope</title>

    <para>The purpose of the Vector, Signal, and Image Processing Library
    (VSIPL) standard is to support portable, high performance application
    programs. The standard is based upon existing libraries that have evolved
    and matured over decades of scientific and engineering computing. A layer
    of abstraction is added to support portability across diverse memory and
    processor architectures. The primary design focus of the standard has been
    embedded signal processing platforms. Enhanced portability of workstation
    applications is a side benefit.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Platform Requirements</title>

    <para>VSIPL was specified so that it could be implemented on a wide
    variety of hardware. In order to use VSIPL functions on a given platform,
    a VSIPL compliant library must be available for the particular hardware
    and tool-set (linker) available for the operating system. Since the
    library API is defined for ANSI C, for practical applications, an ANSI C
    compiler will also be necessary.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Functionality</title>

    <para>This specification provides a number of functions to the programmer
    to support high performance numerical computation on dense rectangular
    arrays. These are organized in the VSIPL documentation according to
    category. The available categories include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Support</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Library initialization and finalization</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Object creation and interaction</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Memory management</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Basic Scalar Operations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Basic Vector Operations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Random Number Generation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Signal Processing</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>FFT operations</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Filtering</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Correlation and convolution</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linear Algebra</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Basic matrix operations</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Linear system solution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Least-squares problem solution</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conformance</title>

    <para>Although there are many functions in this specification, not all
    functions are available in all implementations. The contents of a specific
    VSIPL library subset are defined in a <emphasis>profile</emphasis>. As of
    the completion of VSIPL 1.0 two profiles have been approved by the VSIPL
    Forum, referred to as the "Core" and "Core Lite" profiles. The "Core"
    profile includes most of the signal processing and matrix algebra
    functionality of the library. The “Core Lite” profile includes a smaller
    subset, suitable for vector-based signal processing applications. The
    VSIPL specification defines more functions than are present in either of
    these profiles.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>VSIPL Objects</title>

    <para>The main difference between the proposed VSIPL standard and existing
    libraries is a cleaner encapsulation of memory management through an
    “object-based” design. In VSIPL, a block can be thought of as a contiguous
    area of memory for storage of data. A block consists of a data array,
    which is the memory used for data storage; and a block object, which is an
    abstract data type which stores information necessary for VSIPL to access
    the data array. VSIPL allows the user to construct a view of the data in a
    block as a vector, matrix, or higher dimensional object. A view consists
    of a block, which contains the data of interest; and a view object, which
    is an abstract data type which stores information necessary for VSIPL to
    access the data of interest.</para>

    <para>Blocks and views are opaque. They can only be created, accessed and
    destroyed via library functions. Object data members are private to hide
    the details of non-portable memory hierarchy management. VSIPL library
    developers may hide information peculiar to their implementations in the
    objects in order to prevent the application programmer from accidentally
    writing code that is neither portable nor compatible.</para>

    <para>Data arrays in VSIPL exist in one of two logical data spaces. These
    are the user data space, and VSIPL data space. VSIPL functions may only
    operate on data in VSIPL space. User supplied functions may only operate
    on data in user space. Data may be moved between these logical spaces.
    Depending on the specific implementation, this move may incur actual data
    movement penalties or may simply be a bookkeeping procedure. The user
    should consider the data in VSIPL space to be inaccessible except through
    VSIPL functions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Features of the Specification</title>

    <para>The VSIPL specification provides support for multiple floating-point
    and integer data types. In addition, methods are defined for a vendor to
    supply tools to allow the user to specify precision requirements in an
    application. For example, a user may specify that at least 16 bits of
    precision are needed. On an embedded platform, this might translate
    exactly to a 16-bit type, while on a workstation during development the
    actual type used might have 32 bits of precision. VSIPL allows the same
    code to work on both platforms.</para>

    <para revisionflag="deleted">Two versions of the library are described, referred to as
    development and performance libraries. These libraries operate the same
    with the exception of error reporting and timing. Performance versions of
    a VSIPL library are not guaranteed to provide any error detection or
    handling except in the case of memory allocation. Other programming errors
    under a VSIPL performance library may have unpredictable results, up to
    and including complete system crashes. Development libraries are expected
    to run slower than performance libraries but include more error detection
    capabilities. Suppliers of VSIPL compliant libraries are not required to
    provide both versions; they may choose to supply either version, both
    versions, or a single library that supports both development and
    performance modes, as desired.</para>
    
   <para revisionflag="added">Function pages include a description of the functionality, prototypes,
   argument descriptions, return values, restrictions, errors, notes and references,
   examples, and related functions.  The description of the functions, prototypes, 
   argument descriptions, and return values specify the particular function and how to 
   use it.  The example section shows how the function is used in an application.</para>
   
   <para revisionflag="added">The intent of the sections on restrictions, errors, and notes and references
   are to provide guidance to both the VSIPL user and VSIPL implementer.  VSIPL 
   is capable of supporting a development mode to support code development as well as a
   performance mode for the best performance.  Restrictions are errors that are unlikely to 
   be checked by any implementation.  An example would be checking for a zero divide in
   vsip_vdiv_f.  The restrictions also indicate that these errors may not have predictable 
   results among implementations.  In the zero divde case, one implementation may cause a 
   floating point exception while another might return 0.  Errors are programming errors 
   that will likely be ignored by a performance mode implementation, but should be detected 
   by a development mode implementation.  An example would be calling vsip_finalize((void *)0) 
   without vsip_init(void *)0) being called before it.  A development mode implementation 
   should communicate this problem to the user.  Notes and references are intended as 
   guidance to the user.</para>
   
   <para revisionflag="added">Suppliers of VSIPL compliant libraries are not required to implement both development and
   performance mode versions.  They may choose to implement either version, both versions, or a single library 
   that supports both development and performance modes.  Development mode and performance mode versions should 
   work similarly.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="concepts.xml"/>
</chapter>
