<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="sort" 
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Sort Functions</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The goal of this clause is to define functionality for sorting VSIPL
    vectors. No matrix sort is currently defined although it is
    straightforward to write user functions which will accomplish simple sorts
    by row or column using the vector sort.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Sort Fundamentals</title>

      <para>All sort functionality in VSIPL is defined only on data of type
      real. Vectors of type complex may be sorted using gather functionality
      and an index vector (see select sort section below).</para>

      <para>Sorts are done in place. If the original vector is desired, it
      must be copied to a new vector before calling the function.</para>

      <para>If an index vector which records the sort permutation is desired,
      then an index vector should be created and passed in as an argument. If
      the index vector argument is NULL, then the sort permutation is not
      recorded. A bool argument of VSIP_TRUE for fill indicates that the
      (nonnull) index vector should be initialized as a ramp starting at zero
      with a unit increment. A bool argument of VSIP_FALSE for fill means the
      input index vector values should not be modified. The input index vector
      is permuted element-wise to match the permutation of the data
      vector.</para>

      <para>Note that, for instance, a returned index vector that was
      initialized with the fill argument set to true will allow the
      permutation of an associated vector by using VSIPL gather
      functionality.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Select Sort</title>

        <para>A function called select sort was originally envisioned for this
        section; however it quickly became complicated. The API was
        complicated to design, and the function was hard to write and
        difficult to use. The ideas behind select sort are straightforward and
        easy to implement using other library functionality, and performance
        gains from a dedicated function don’t seem to be worthwhile. So
        instead of select sort this section is included as a clue to better
        optimize your sorts. The section also supplies clues on why we have
        included the index vector as part of the sort functionality.</para>

        <para>There are many different requirements for sorting which are
        application specific. In particular one may have a very large amount
        of data to sort through even though only a small portion is of
        interest. For instance data greater than some value; or there may be
        some other condition or a set of conditions which define the data of
        interest.</para>

        <para>The point here is that it is computationally expensive to sort
        data and sorting data of no interest is not efficient. Before doing
        the sort first the application should prune off unwanted values using
        logical and/or selection operations. Boolean vector result of
        true/false values from the logical operators can be turned into index
        vectors using the indexbool function (see selection operations from
        the main specification). Gather functionality allows the collection of
        the proper data to be sorted. If an index relationship back to the
        original data is required, then the index vector from the boolean
        operation which is used to gather the boolean data is passed in as the
        index argument and the fill flag is set to false. This index vector is
        permuted to match the data permutation and the index relationship of
        the sorted data back to the original vector is maintained.</para>

        <para>This type sorting is also used for sorting complex vectors.
        Since only vectors of type real may be sorted the implication is that
        the complex vector must have some operation on it that converts it
        from complex to real. By maintaining an index vector through all the
        operations and passing this into sort then the sort results may be
        translated back to the complex data.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Type Definitions for Sort</title>

      <para>The following are type definitions for VSIPL sort
      functionality.</para>

      <synopsis>typedef enum 
{
  VSIP_SORT_ASCENDING = 0,
  VSIP_SORT_DESCENDING = 1
} vsip_sort_dir;
typedef enum 
{
  VSIP_SORT_BYVALUE = 0,
  VSIP_SORT_BYMAGNITUDE = 1,
} vsip_sort_mode;</synopsis>

      <para>The enumerated value VSIP_SORT_ASCENDING will cause a sort so that
      the smaller value after the mode condition is evaluated has the smaller
      index (smallest to largest).</para>

      <para>The enumerated value VSIP_SORT_DESCENDING will cause a sort so
      that the largest value after the mode condition is evaluated has the
      smaller index (largest to smallest).</para>

      <para>The enumerated value VSIP_SORT_BYVALUE will cause the value to be
      sorted as is.</para>

      <para>The enumerated value VSIP_SORT_BYMAGNITUDE will cause the sort to
      be done on the absolute value.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sort</title>

    <para>The following man pages represent sort operations defined in
    VSIPL.</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><function>vsip_vsortip_p</function></entry>

            <entry>Vector sort in-place.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <section xml:id="vsortip">
      <title>vsip_vsortip_<replaceable>p</replaceable></title>

      <para>Sort data in a vector.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Functionality</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Sort a data vector in ascending or descending order either
            by value or by magnitude. If a valid index vector is included as
            the index argument, then that vector is permuted to match the
            permutation of the data vector. If the boolean fill argument is
            true and the index vector is valid, then the index vector is
            initialized with a ramp index starting at zero with increment one.
            If the index vector is null, it and the fill flag are
            ignored.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Prototypes</term>

          <listitem>
            <synopsis>void vsip_vsortip_p(const vsip_vview_p *a, vsip_sort_mode mode, 
                    vsip_sort_dir dir, vsip_bool fill, const vsip_vview_vi *index);</synopsis>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Arguments</term>

          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>a</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Vector/Matrix view of input/output data.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>mode</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sort type.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>dir</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sort direction.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>fill</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Indicates if the function should initialize the index
                  vector (VSIP_TRUE); or assume the index vector has already
                  been initialized (VSIP_FALSE).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>index</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>An index vector of the proper type to store the
                  original index of the sorted values or null if no index
                  vector is desired. The length of a non-null index vector
                  index length must match the total number of values in the
                  input views.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Return value</term>

          <listitem>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Restrictions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Errors</term>

          <listitem>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The index argument must be a valid index vector or
                NULL.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The views must be conformant.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The view objects must be valid.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Arguments for mode, dir, and fill must be valid.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Notes/References</term>

          <listitem>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Examples</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This example creates a complex vector of random values and
            then sorts the vector according to magnitude.</para>

            <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/sort.c" parse="text"/></programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>See Also</term>

          <listitem>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
