<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="foreword" 
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Foreword</title>

  <para>The VSIPL++ Library provides C++ classes and functions for writing
  embedded signal processing applications designed to run on one or more
  processors. VSIPL++ contains</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>containers such as vectors, matrixes, and tensors,</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>mathematical operations such as addition and matrix multiplication
      on these containers,</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>complex numbers and random numbers,</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>various linear algebra operations including solvers using LU, QR,
      and singular value decomposition methods, and</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>signal processing classes and functions including fast Fourier
      transforms, convolutions, correlations, FIR filters, and IIR
      filters.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The VSIPL++ specification has been split into two
  overlapping documents, covering uniprocessor execution and multi-processor
  execution. Uniprocessor execution is specified in the <olink
  targetdoc="vsiplxx"></olink>, while distributed execution is specified
  here.</para>

  <para>This distributed specification is significantly shorter than the
  uniprocessor specification because the library has been carefully designed
  to support running the same programs in either single or multiple processor
  modes. This specification contains means to specify how a container’s contents
  are distributed among available processors. Mathematical operations and
  other operations on those containers need not be re-specified because the
  toolkit automatically ensures data is moved to where it is used so that
  valid serial and parallel programs have the same effect.</para>

  <para>Please visit the <link xlink:href="http://www.hpec-si.org">High
  Performance Embedded Computing Software Initiative webpage</link> for more
  information on VSIPL++ and for reference implementations.</para>
</preface>
