<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="intro" 
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <titleabbrev>intro</titleabbrev>

  <section xml:id="intro.scope">
    <title>Scope</title>

    <titleabbrev>intro.scope</titleabbrev>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>This document specifies requirements for implementations of the
        VSIPL++ Library.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The VSIPL++ Library is a C++ programming interface for
        performing linear algebra and signal processing computations.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For classes and class templates, this document specifies partial
        definitions. Private members are not specified, but each
        implementation shall supply them to complete the definitions according
        to the descriptions given herein.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For functions, function templates, objects, and values, this
        document specifies complete or partial declarations. Implementations
        shall supply definitions consistent with the descriptions given
        herein.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="intro.refs">
    <title>Normative references</title>

    <titleabbrev>intro.refs</titleabbrev>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following standard contains provisions which, through
        reference in this text, constitute provisions of this standard. At the
        time of publication, the editions indicated were valid. All standards
        are subject to revision, and users of this standard are encouraged to
        investigate the possibility of applying the most recent editions of
        the standard indicated below.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>ISO/IEC 14882, Programming languages — C++</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The VSIPL++ Parallel Specification is incorporated via
        reference.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>References to “VSIPL” or the “VSIPL
        specification” refer to the VSIPL specification at <link
        xlink:href="http://www.omg.org/spec/VSIPL/">http://www.omg.org/spec/VSIPL/</link><ulink
        href="http://www.omg.org/spec/VSIPL/"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="intro.compliance">
    <title>Compliance</title>

    <titleabbrev>intro.compliance</titleabbrev>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Most functions in this specification are
        parametrized for the value-types they operate on. The individual
        function specifications indicate which value-types need to be
        supported in a compliant implementation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Compliance criteria relating to the VSIPL++ Parallel
        specification are listed in <olink targetdoc="vsiplxx-par"
        targetptr="dpp.oplevel"/></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All implementations must define the macro VSIP_HAS_EXCEPTIONS in
        &lt;vsip/support.hpp&gt; to a constant-expression such that in:</para>

        <para><code>#if VSIP_HAS_EXCEPTIONS</code></para>

        <para><constant>VSIP_HAS_EXCEPTIONS</constant> evaluates to a non-zero
        value if and only if the implementation throws the exceptions
        indicated by “Throws” clauses in this specification.</para>

        <para>If <constant>VSIP_HAS_EXCEPTIONS</constant> evaluates to zero,
        then, in all situations where this specification would otherwise
        require that an exception be thrown, the behavior is undefined.
        Implementations that do not support exceptions must provide an
        implementation-defined way to report memory allocation errors to the
        user.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="intro.ack">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <titleabbrev>intro.ack</titleabbrev>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The VSIPL++ Library as described in this standard is based on
        the VSIPL 1.3 API by David A. Schwartz, Randall R. Judd, William J.
        Harrod, and Dwight P. Manley, 2002 June 11, as approved by the VSIPL
        Forum, copyright © 1999–2002 Georgia Tech Research Corporation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
